<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ed Latimore</title>
    <description>Website of Ed Latimore, undefeated heavy-weight boxer, writer, and physicist
</description>
    <link>http://moss-gorilla1.cloudvent.net/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://moss-gorilla1.cloudvent.net/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2016 16:35:28 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2016 16:35:28 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Victoria Amat Curam</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Victoria Amat Curam.&lt;/strong&gt; This is Latin for “Victory loves preparation”. This is perhaps my favorite saying and a code I live by. Being smart helps and being tough keeps you in the fight, but preparation is king and keeps you from relying on might. This is why my first shirt carries this banner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve was never into the idea of putting my name on the back of shirts for guys to wear. I’m an unusual fighter this way. I don’t want people to wear a bunch of “Team Latimore” shirts. Guys who sale shirts have approached me with variations of the idea and I wasn’t a fan. If I’m going to sell something to people, I want to sell the something that is representative of the mindset and ideas that I embrace. So as they say, if you want something done then do it yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ed Latimore is a cool sounding name. Hopefully one day people around the world know it even after I die. “Victoria Amat Curam” is a lifestyle and a mentality. People who practice it will always succeed over those who don’t. This will be true until the sun explodes and ends life as we know it. If you buy from me you’re getting a saying I hold near and dear. Victory loves preparation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://edlatimore.com/merchandise/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/versions/vacmen2-150x150---x----150-150x---.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://edlatimore.com/merchandise/&quot;&gt;Click here to get men or women’s in all colors and sizes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chess knight is my favorite piece in the game. Its the only piece in the game that is not limited by what’s in front of it. It’s the only piece in the game that can jump over the opposition. It’s the piece that strikes terror into most players because through it’s careful use it can attack and defend many pieces at once. The only way to appreciate a piece with power of this magnitude is to be prepared. Victory loves preparation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a competitor in any arena–intellectual, physical or even just fighting the daily struggle of life–this is a saying that you can always think of when you aren’t sure of the next step. Relax and prepare.  You can’t be ready for everything but you can be ready for most things. Because you’ll be prepared for the rest of what can go wrong, your brain can go on autopilot and you can focus on dealing with the new problem with great efficacy. Victoria Amat Curam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No one’s life ever got worse by planning. Failing to plan is planning to fail.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2016 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://moss-gorilla1.cloudvent.net/2016/06/20/victoria-amat-curam/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://moss-gorilla1.cloudvent.net/2016/06/20/victoria-amat-curam/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Don&#39;t Make Enemies For Free</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Escalation of force. The standard of force continuum. Rules of engagement. Regardless of the name it goes by the concept is the same: use no more force than necessary to neutralize opposition. There is a beautiful poem of sorts in martial arts that sums up this idea neatly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is better to avoid than to block, It is better to block than to strike, It is better to strike than to hurt, It is better to hurt than to maim, It is better to maim than to kill, It is better to kill than to be killed, All life is precious and none can be replaced”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You do what you have to do to stop someone from hurting you, but no more than that. Compassionate aggression. Damage control. Do just enough to stop your opponent from hurting you. Force escalation is practiced to avoid damage that could ultimately result in an unnecessary fatality. For the less compassionate in the audience–the ones all about throwing blows in a vocal confrontation, stomping a dude out that’s already down, or even dumping a box of bullets into a guy that got the best of you–there is a more practical reason for following this code. If you can’t justify your use of force in a court of law, then you could get anything from aggravated assault to manslaughter. The length of time varies, but jail is jail and all of you reading this should be saying “fuck that!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So aside from the practical implications–like staying out of prison–there is another reason you don’t want to overdue it when you take down opposition in your life. Every action in human affairs provokes a reaction of unknown force that is limited only by the power of those to react. There are times when you have to block, hurt, maim or maybe even kill. This could be in business, interpersonal relationships or daily life. Figurative and literal situations apply. But if you focus on achieving your objective instead of destroying the other person, then you might save yourself the wrath of new a enemy. On the other hand, he still might hate you anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the risk you take whenever you block someones path or strike them down. Even if it’s necessary, you never meet a villain that feels like he needs to be stop. But sometimes the villain can become your ally. A crushed rival will remember not only how you beat him, but how you behaved once your hand was raised in victory. You’ve already won! There is no need to throw salt in a lethal wound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s amazing how many people make enemies in situations where nothing is gained at all. You might have to strike an opponent, but you don’t have to maim or kill him. This increases the chances that he comes for revenge. Or his friends may come for revenge. Hell knoweth no fury than an opponent driven by hatred rather than necessity. No one knows the future. Overly shamed or overly hurt opponents become enemies who will use their own methods and resources to balance the emotional scales. No man knows the hour and intensity of his own revenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;youve-already-won-there-is-no-need-to-throw-salt-in-a-lethal-wound&quot;&gt;You’ve already won! There is no need to throw salt in a lethal wound.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you have to stop an opponent, do what’s necessary and respect your adversary. If he becomes a bitter enemy anyway, there is nothing you could have done. Just don’t make an enemy out of the fallen if you don’t have to. The difference between those who graciously accept defeat and those who plot revenge is often how the victor handles the temporary shift of power. The enemy you avoid making today could be your ally tomorrow. Or your executioner.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jun 2016 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://moss-gorilla1.cloudvent.net/2016/06/12/don-t-make-enemies-for-free/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://moss-gorilla1.cloudvent.net/2016/06/12/don-t-make-enemies-for-free/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Becoming A Problem To Solve Your Problems</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When faced with any type of opposition, there is one thing you can do that will always make winning significantly easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have used this tool in my chess games, my boxing matches, with bullies when I was younger, and with bosses and coworkers who may have been annoying or stifling. It works in street fights and it works in civil negotiations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The beauty of this particular thing is that, while having skill and technique help, it is not necessary to be successful when using it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While success may not be guaranteed (are there ever any guarantees in life?), you will come out of many situations with the upper hand—if not decidedly victorious—if you do this one thing when you can do nothing else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is this magically simple technique that anyone, regardless of the level of skill they face in their opposition, can use to give themselves a better chance of victory?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;become-a-problem&quot;&gt;Become a Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is this: become a problem. Or rather, become a problem in such a way that your opposition will flounder, clueless, attempting to effectively deal with you. By definition, you are already a problem; your existence is in the way of what someone else wants. After all, it wouldn’t be much of a fight if there wasn’t someone to struggle against and, let’s be honest, you wouldn’t be negotiating if you were already in a position to get everything you want without making concessions to another party. And, sometimes, you show up to the gunfight and your ammo is not quite what you expected. You’ve got to get creative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could spell it out for you, but I’ve always found examples to be an effective teaching method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I play chess, one of the most mentally demanding games; some of the most annoying and strange situations in a chess game arise when your opponent makes some… interesting… moves that force you to reconsider your strategy. There is an expected line of play then your opponent deviates sharply from it. He moves this, you move that, he moves this, and so on. While it’s not exactly scripted, over time history has shown that certain lines of play are more effective than others. But when someone deviates from the “script,” does something out of the ordinary, you need to shift your thinking from what’s routine and expected in order to deal with this new play. This idea—forcing someone to deal with what they weren’t expecting to deal with—is key and will be revisited shortly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also glean insight into this idea by considering how it works in a fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days, my fighting is conducted in a manner more condoned by the public, in the ring. But, when I was younger, I was involved in more than a few street fights. I was not a violent kid naturally, but when you grow up in circumstances like I did, you quickly learn that not only are there some people that just like being ornery assholes, these people expect you kowtow to them in fear. When I was about ten or eleven years old, I got a lesson in dealing with these assholes. Back then, day after day, a new neighborhood kid would pick on me until this one day my mom had enough. She marched me back to the playground I had just been run out of and issued an open challenge to every single kid that bothered me. I think I ended up fighting five kids that day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’d think that’d be enough, but I think I got my ass kicked so they didn’t take me seriously. However, each time one of them started anything, we went through the same process again. If one kid started a fight, I ended up challenging every kid around that day and they either backed down or we got into a scuffle where they were beat up. Very few people enjoy being beaten, and they weren’t some of the few. It got to the point that, by the end of that summer, people were actively checking other people that attempted to fight me because it just wasn’t worth the cost of doing business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://edlatimore.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/fighting.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;This dude better become a problem REAL fast&quot; /&gt;This dude better become a problem REAL fast&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve seen the same thing in boxing. There was a fighter in our amateur circuit that was a big fan of holding. I mean, a little hugging is normal, but this guy took it to extremes. He’d sneak little annoying shots in while he’s doing it, making the whole fight an ugly affair. I can’t tell you how many times this style of fighting frustrated the hell out of his opponents. They got so frustrated they’d abandon the ability to concentrate effectively, thus ending up the losers. I don’t think this guy is one of the most skilled fighters ever, but he certainly had an impressive list of accolades. Most people simply don’t want to—or can’t—fight that kind of fight so they cave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And therein lies the reason why becoming a basic, unique problem works in almost any situation. Very few people have the ability to adjust to problems in real time. They expect things to go a certain way and when there is a deviation from what they anticipated, their minds go to shit. Now, if you come against someone that is capable of making such adjustments—and these creative, dynamic individuals are few and far between in most arenas—there’s nothing you could have done to win anyway. But sometimes, it’s a good to test someone’s tolerance for an unexpected response by being problematic in an unfamiliar way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2016 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://moss-gorilla1.cloudvent.net/2016/06/08/becoming-a-problem-to-solve-your-problems/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://moss-gorilla1.cloudvent.net/2016/06/08/becoming-a-problem-to-solve-your-problems/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Courage In Violence</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Boxing is a poor man’s sport; most of us come from the ghetto to the ring. It’s a natural transition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the hood, if you’re willing to commit violence, you get respect. In boxing, the most violent man is usually the winner and the winner gets respect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the loser gets respect if he fights hard and brings the heat. But unlike the street, there are rules in a boxing match.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was at a sparring session with two rival gyms. Things were getting heated. One of the dudes sparring got caught with a shot he didn’t like and it escalated quickly. In an instant it looked more like a brawl than a match, with members from each side jumping in. Fortunately, the coaches got things under control before they got too out of control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, Coach then told something I’ll never forget. He said,“If you do this shit in the street, someone’s probably gonna get killed. You kill someone in the street and you’re going to jail. But if you do it in the ring, you ain’t goin’ nowhere. Shit, they gonna clap and cheer your name if you do it during the fight.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, everyone calmed down and the sparring session continued. The dudes were cool after that. It takes a lot of courage, skill, and discipline to get the best of a man when he is prepared and trained and ready for you and you have to meet him on equal footing. That doesn’t happen when you run up to someone and sucker punch them or take out a gun and shoot them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being prepared, ready for the ring is teaching a man to face his fears head on because the only advantages he can be confident of are found in training and preparation. Taking out that gun, running up to a man on the street to beat him down is a coward’s way, a moment where he faces no real possibility of defeat. That shit works if you have to go to war or save your family, but for building true character you need to build courage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The violence inherent to a boxing match is an excellent method to build courage. There is always a winner and a loser. Even when the judges declare a bullshit draw, everyone knows that someone won and someone lost. It’s only through facing the possibility of getting hurt, losing or dying, that you can ever build actual courage. There ain’t a lot of things left in the world that lets a man face those fears and grow from facing them. Boxing is one of the few remaining forms of violence that lets you live another day while developing your courage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The violence inherent to a boxing match is an excellent method to build courage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those kids at the session got into a brawl because they had learned to be violent, to take the coward’s way. Sometimes, that shit is necessary—especially in the streets. But if you wanna be better than the streets, you gotta learn to be courageous. If you want to be courageous in the face violence—where another man can legally kill you and be applauded—you can be courageous anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 29 May 2016 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://moss-gorilla1.cloudvent.net/2016/05/29/courage-in-violence/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://moss-gorilla1.cloudvent.net/2016/05/29/courage-in-violence/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>5 Reasons You Should Not Go To College</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;So it’s time to beat this horse again even though its been &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.goodlookingloser.com/entry/college/misconceptions-about-college-part-1&quot;&gt;killed numerous times&lt;/a&gt;. At the very least we’re going to make sure it thinks long and hard before it resurrects itself for another round. My unique perspective on this issue is that I am actually in college as an adult. I fully realize there are many successful people that majored in non-stem subjects just as there are unemployed engineers (somewhere, I’m sure). But I like to play the odds that are in my favor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you aren’t planning to major in a STEM (science, technology, engineering or mathematics) field you should not go to college. Even if you plan on majoring in certain STEM topics (biology or anything that can remotely be considered a social science), you should skip out. College is a raw deal for most people and here’s why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Debt&lt;/strong&gt;. On average, you’re going to borrow about 6 figures. When you combine interest and cost of living, you aren’t going to make enough to deal with that financial burden unless you have a STEM degree salary. And that’s if you can find work that relates to what you studied…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Job availability&lt;/strong&gt;. When it comes to finding jobs, there’s the good and there’s the bad of it. The good is that there are a lot of them. The bad is that you either can’t get them without STEM or trade training or you don’t want them because they don’t pay enough and/or have shitty hours. We live in an era that is tech and service industry heavy. If you aren’t involved in one of the skilled trades, you are almost certainly going to end up in the service industry or doing some low level administrative work. Either way, you aren’t going to make enough money to afford much of a life AND pay off that heavy debt you took out with the hope of living the life you want to lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Job availability, part 2&lt;/strong&gt;. Working at a Starbucks some years ago, I learned something they don’t tell you in school. At the time, I was a 21 year old barista making 7.25 an hour. Every one of my co-workers, with the exception of one girl younger than me, had a college degree. This was not uncommon. A lot of baristas were making 600 a month + tip with college degrees. How does this happen? Half of it’s majoring in bullshit (i.e., not STEM) and the other half is because of the over-abundance of college educated people. If everyone goes to college and earns a degree, you no longer stand out and a college degree is worth about as much to an employer as a high school diploma was maybe fifteen years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, your degree needs to be in something rare and difficult (like STEM); otherwise, you end up competing for a bunch of low paying jobs because that is all that is left. The low paying jobs now have two pools of applicants—those without degrees and those with. For a host of reasons (some obvious, some not), applicants with college degrees are more highly desired. The availability of jobs in other areas becomes diluted as people overload positions that require degrees like biology and social science so they then get relegated to administrative jobs and people just keep getting bumped down. These people are bumped down until they’re baristas, barely making enough for rent with 6 figures of debt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Skills&lt;/strong&gt;. You need skills to pay bills. Period. College may grant you a pretty piece of paper, but it will not necessarily teach you skills. You need to learn how to fix electronics, program a computer, repair a car, do plumbing or carpentry, or speak a foreign language if you are looking for the guarantee of a decent paycheck. As the baristas I worked with learned, there are no guarantees. On the flip side, Google is famous for hiring programmers with no formal training. Skills guarantee money. A piece of paper, however nice to look at framed and hanging in your parents’ home, will not.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://moss-gorilla1.cloudvent.net/2016/05/24/5-reasons-you-should-not-go-to-college/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://moss-gorilla1.cloudvent.net/2016/05/24/5-reasons-you-should-not-go-to-college/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Crucible</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, I found myself in the middle of my boxing training session. Instead of the usual dose of educational work that would drill an attacking pattern into my head, the focus of the second session was for continuous repetition of a set of four attacking patterns I’d learned the day before. “How many punches can you throw in a round” was never a question asked. It was assumed I’d punch the mits non-stop. I’d punch the mits non-stop for six three minute rounds. This was on top of running my usual three and a half miles in the morning, the morning training session, and the excruciatingly difficult calisthenics that followed. This was not a day for the light of heart. Yet, I looked forward to it.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you wish to improve, when you start on the course to improvement, there are hard days and there are easy days. When you first start on this course, there are many more hard days. Then, they become more and more infrequent as you progress. This is because new facets of the skill become easier to learn due to previous acquisition. You must pour the foundation before building the first floor. Once that first floor is built, it’s easier to build the second and the third. The more floors you build, the easier it is to build the next one because you are now familiar with the building plan. This is especially true if all the floors you build are laid out exactly the same. But what happens when someone wants to put an addition on that deviates from the work done before it? What happens when you encounter a new skill set you must acquire and it seems entirely dissimilar to what you have been doing? You enter a place I’ve come to affectionately call “The Crucible.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://moss-gorilla1.cloudvent.net/img/posts/kungfu.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kung-Fu&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Crucible” isn’t from that play by Arthur Miller or that so-so flick starring Daniel Day Lewis and a surprisingly plain looking Winona Ryder. Merriam-Webster offers a fantastic definition of exactly what a crucible is: a place or situation in which concentrated forces interact to cause influence, change, or development. This Crucible is present in every ability or talent a human being could wish to develop. As you endeavor to gain some mastery of a craft, this is what is supposed to happen:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learn and practice something new. This makes you better than a novice.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learn and practice the fundamentals. This makes you better than average.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focus on what you’re good at and excel. This makes you good.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focus on what you’re terrible at and excel. This makes you great.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an oversimplified version of how a person improves at something. However, many people are content reaching step three because step four requires an extraordinary amount of discomfort. Very few people ever enter the top ten percent in a particular skill because most people do not want to deal with the stress it takes to get there—whether it is physical, mental, social, or spiritual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the problem: a great number of us are content to just be “good enough” at something. You see it all the time. Guys content being just good enough to date a girl that isn’t fat, but acts like a bitch. Athletes content being just good enough they don’t look bad. Employees that are content to be just good enough at their job to get a small raise each year. The students who are content to be just good enough to pass the class or please the teacher or whatever it is they’re looking for. This mediocrity is enough to keep you from looking like a failure, but if you’re ever compared to the big dogs you’d be blown out of the water. That’s fine, sure, but we here are in the business of excellence, of winning. Most other people will never visit The Crucible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-great-number-of-us-are-content-to-just-be-good-enough-at-something&quot;&gt;A great number of us are content to just be “good enough” at something&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t blame them. The Crucible is a miserable, depressingly realistic place, free from the illusion of grandeur. It’s the path from good to great. The skills you’ve avoided working on because other parts of your skill set were good enough to get you somewhere now mock you at every repetition, at every hour you put in. You may realize you are so bad at something that is essential to your becoming great at your skill set that you totally throw in the towel. That’s okay. It’s not for everyone. Some people don’t even try. At least you tried. It’s easy to avoid The Crucible if you are afraid of the work or you have no interest in being better than what you are now. However, even if you attempt and fail, you will still have improved more than the person that challenges you for a particular position where there are fewer spots than the one you occupy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;But, remember this: the only way to excel and surpass others, be great, is to make sure that you take regular visits to The Crucible.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2016 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://moss-gorilla1.cloudvent.net/2016/05/16/the-crucible/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://moss-gorilla1.cloudvent.net/2016/05/16/the-crucible/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Time: An Investment</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, I found myself in the middle of my boxing training session. Instead of the usual dose of educational work that would drill an attacking pattern into my head, the focus of the second session was for continuous repetition of a set of four attacking patterns I’d learned the day before. “How many punches can you throw in a round” was never a question asked. It was assumed I’d punch the mits non-stop. I’d punch the mits non-stop for six three minute rounds. This was on top of running my usual three and a half miles in the morning, the morning training session, and the excruciatingly difficult calisthenics that followed. This was not a day for the light of heart. Yet, I looked forward to it.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you wish to improve, when you start on the course to improvement, there are hard days and there are easy days. When you first start on this course, there are many more hard days. Then, they become more and more infrequent as you progress. This is because new facets of the skill become easier to learn due to previous acquisition. You must pour the foundation before building the first floor. Once that first floor is built, it’s easier to build the second and the third. The more floors you build, the easier it is to build the next one because you are now familiar with the building plan. This is especially true if all the floors you build are laid out exactly the same. But what happens when someone wants to put an addition on that deviates from the work done before it? What happens when you encounter a new skill set you must acquire and it seems entirely dissimilar to what you have been doing? You enter a place I’ve come to affectionately call “The Crucible.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://moss-gorilla1.cloudvent.net/img/posts/kungfu.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kung-Fu&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Crucible” isn’t from that play by Arthur Miller or that so-so flick starring Daniel Day Lewis and a surprisingly plain looking Winona Ryder. Merriam-Webster offers a fantastic definition of exactly what a crucible is: a place or situation in which concentrated forces interact to cause influence, change, or development. This Crucible is present in every ability or talent a human being could wish to develop. As you endeavor to gain some mastery of a craft, this is what is supposed to happen:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learn and practice something new. This makes you better than a novice.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learn and practice the fundamentals. This makes you better than average.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focus on what you’re good at and excel. This makes you good.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focus on what you’re terrible at and excel. This makes you great.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an oversimplified version of how a person improves at something. However, many people are content reaching step three because step four requires an extraordinary amount of discomfort. Very few people ever enter the top ten percent in a particular skill because most people do not want to deal with the stress it takes to get there—whether it is physical, mental, social, or spiritual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the problem: a great number of us are content to just be “good enough” at something. You see it all the time. Guys content being just good enough to date a girl that isn’t fat, but acts like a bitch. Athletes content being just good enough they don’t look bad. Employees that are content to be just good enough at their job to get a small raise each year. The students who are content to be just good enough to pass the class or please the teacher or whatever it is they’re looking for. This mediocrity is enough to keep you from looking like a failure, but if you’re ever compared to the big dogs you’d be blown out of the water. That’s fine, sure, but we here are in the business of excellence, of winning. Most other people will never visit The Crucible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-great-number-of-us-are-content-to-just-be-good-enough-at-something&quot;&gt;A great number of us are content to just be “good enough” at something&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t blame them. The Crucible is a miserable, depressingly realistic place, free from the illusion of grandeur. It’s the path from good to great. The skills you’ve avoided working on because other parts of your skill set were good enough to get you somewhere now mock you at every repetition, at every hour you put in. You may realize you are so bad at something that is essential to your becoming great at your skill set that you totally throw in the towel. That’s okay. It’s not for everyone. Some people don’t even try. At least you tried. It’s easy to avoid The Crucible if you are afraid of the work or you have no interest in being better than what you are now. However, even if you attempt and fail, you will still have improved more than the person that challenges you for a particular position where there are fewer spots than the one you occupy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;But, remember this: the only way to excel and surpass others, be great, is to make sure that you take regular visits to The Crucible.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 13 May 2016 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://moss-gorilla1.cloudvent.net/2016/05/13/time-an-investment/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://moss-gorilla1.cloudvent.net/2016/05/13/time-an-investment/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Inspiration</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, people ask me to teach my method for staying so motivated. My answer is always the same: I can’t motivate you because I don’t even know how to motivate myself. Either you want something badly enough to do what it takes to get it or you’re content with an average—at best—existence. But, I can &lt;em&gt;inspire&lt;/em&gt; you because I know what it’s like to be inspired. I know how to channel that feel when I feel low. I can tell you how to become inspired to achieve the only thing that matters—the life of your dreams, whatever that dream is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I tell you how, let me do the semantics a bit of justice. Some reading this might argue that there’s no difference between inspiring and motivating someone. Obviously, I’m not part of this camp. If you &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; part of this camp or you’re splitting hairs about the potential overlap of the definition, don’t despair. Rather than tell you to stop reading this article, I’ll break it down. I want you to get something out of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;either-you-want-something-badly-enough-to-do-what-it-takes-to-get-it-or-youre-content-with-an-averageat-bestexistence&quot;&gt;Either you want something badly enough to do what it takes to get it or you’re content with an average—at best—existence.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference between “motivate” and “inspire” is the source of the energy behind the word. &lt;a href=&quot;/2016/01/16/the-right-motivation/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Motivation&lt;/em&gt; is internal&lt;/a&gt;. I don’t do internal because I can’t make you want something. It’s why I will never go in to the personal fitness industry. There is no shortage of information on how to lose weight and I think most people know the basic formula. They need someone to push them through the work because they don’t have the discipline to make it happen by themselves. My hat is off to the guys that can make a good living doing that; I’m not built for it. I’m built for inspiring people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-difference-between-motivate-and-inspire-is-the-source-of-the-energy-behind-the-word&quot;&gt;The difference between “motivate” and “inspire” is the source of the energy behind the word.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inspiration is external.&lt;/strong&gt; You see a lifestyle or set of accomplishments and your immediate reaction is “I want that and I will do what it takes to get it.” The external circumstances inspired you. Now, it’s up to you to sustain the motivation to get the work done. This is why I enjoy training people to pass running tests, providing coaching in my sport, and tutoring. The person is already motivated. They’ve chosen to learn from me because my accomplishments in the discipline they seek to learn couples with the inspiration they received watching others get what they want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trick to getting inspired is to push the limits of your comfort zone. Many people lack the motivation to do better in life because they genuinely don’t know what “better” looks like. Not in any meaningful context, anyway. It’s one thing to see a beach paradise on a show; another, way more inspiring event, to take a trip to your closest beach and experience that setting for yourself. Afterward, you may be inspired to do whatever it takes to get the means to visit the beach often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The beach is my personal favorite place to us as an example because I want to end up there. But, inspiration works like this for the improvement of any face of life. If you see how people fawn over someone with a nice physique, you’ll be inspired to work hard in the gym and eat right. If you see someone with a tight-knit, loving family, it may inspire you to settle down with someone and build a life together. This isn’t to say you’ll remain motivated as you struggle to stick with the work that anything worthwhile requires. But, like I said: I don’t do motivation. The key to becoming inspired is having a real, positive experience that differs from your normal, day-to-day life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-trick-to-getting-inspired-is-to-push-the-limits-of-your-comfort-zone&quot;&gt;The trick to getting inspired is to push the limits of your comfort zone.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inspiration can also go the other way. I know quite a few people that have decided to stop smoking or stop drinking or clean up their diet after they have watched a loved one perish from the result of those habits. Having a close brush with death as a result of these habits also inspires a person to change. The inspiration comes from a real experience that has a negative effect so different from what you’re used to that you’re forced to a new path of action. It’s one thing to read the surgeon general’s warning on a pack of cigarettes; it’s another thing entirely watching your father die of lung cancer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When you can’t find the motivation to make changes—to add to the good or diminish the bad—there is a good chance you aren’t properly inspired. You don’t even have something you strongly desire to avoid or attain yet.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To become inspired, always seek new experiences. Each new experience shows you a part of the world that you didn’t realize existed. Once you find something that lights your fire, THEN you will burn with the motivation to accomplish it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To become inspired to kick a habit, get as close to the negative consequences as you can. YouTube searches for videos of people in drunk driving accidents or chemotherapy might change your life. Meditate on how terrible it would be to experience this. Every time I’m in the care and I contemplate texting while driving, I think about how expensive a fender bender would be. Then, I imagine how much worse it will be going 40 MPH. And I put my phone down. Imagine what it’s like to meet your end as a result of your terrible habit and how much life you’re losing as a result. If that doesn’t inspire you, nothing will.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 07 May 2016 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://moss-gorilla1.cloudvent.net/2016/05/07/the-inspiration/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://moss-gorilla1.cloudvent.net/2016/05/07/the-inspiration/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Purpose Of Emotions: The Map And The Road</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Everything has a purpose. That purpose may not be profound, but you feel a variety of emotions for a reason. Emotions are your internal reaction to your external environment. Before you can have a reaction to something, you compare it to your own thoughts, feelings, and beliefs. You are checking to see if the way it appears is the way you believe it should be. When a situation meets expectations and you approve of it, you experience positive emotions. If the situation runs contrary to your expectations or you disapprove of it, you experience negative emotions. To summarize this, &lt;strong&gt;your emotional reaction represents the congruence between your perception and the actuality of the world.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an old saying: “When the map and the road disagree, the map is wrong.” To appreciate the application of this saying to emotions, you must also remember that your emotions are based solely on perception. There is always more than one way to see a person or event. Our perceptions, perspectives, and beliefs—our map—are formed by what we think the world should look like. When our map is compared to the world and the world looks different, we have a choice to make. We can continue to wander around aimlessly and hope to get somewhere or we can discard the map and select a new one. Your emotions serve as a way for you to evaluate your perspective of the world around you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-the-map-and-the-road-disagree-the-map-is-wrong&quot;&gt;“When the map and the road disagree, the map is wrong.”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that I did not include “change the road” as one of the options. This is because that can be extremely difficult and it will not increase your emotional control. Reality is very difficult to change. There are some fundamental things about people and the world that you must accept, that you must shape your strategy for living around. I could make a list of things in the world you must learn to accept and manage, but I’d never cover everything that could arise or has arisen. Instead, here’s a generally precise guide: if it falls outside of a thing you can control, then you have no choice but to accept that it’s a part of reality. &lt;strong&gt;The only thing you can actually control is yourself and what you can influence is surprisingly limited.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;changing-the-road-is-never-an-option&quot;&gt;Changing the road is never an option&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just because you are forced to accept something does not mean that you are forced to accept your own perception of it. This is because you have control of your perceptions and thoughts. &lt;strong&gt;Changing your perception does not change the event, but it will change how you feel about it&lt;/strong&gt;. Since your perception of something is responsible for how you feel about it, changing your thought process about it can give you the ability to change how you feel towards it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s return to the map analogy. The road is reality and the map is our perception of reality. Our perception of events in reality lead to our emotional reaction. When the map and the road are in disagreement, it would be a waste of energy and time to try and rebuild a whole new road so that your map makes sense. The road is beyond your control, having been there long before you. It will continue to exist long after you. A more sensible course of action—one that is completely within your control—is to find a map that works better for where you want to go. The trip is the journey through life and the destination depends entirely upon what you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The analogy between the map and your emotions allows us to have many more useful insights into the purpose of our emotions. When we use a map to navigate to a destination, we are exerting control over the path we take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-road-is-beyond-your-control-having-been-there-long-before-you-it-will-continue-to-exist-long-after-you&quot;&gt;The road is beyond your control, having been there long before you. It will continue to exist long after you.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two ways a person can arrive at a destination. They can take a reactive or a proactive method. Trying to get to a place in a reactive manner means that you aren’t really sure if you’re going the best way. Instead, you adjust your path based on the things that don’t work—dead ends, getting lost, and unexp&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2016 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://moss-gorilla1.cloudvent.net/2016/05/05/the-purpose-of-emotions-the-map-and-the-road/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://moss-gorilla1.cloudvent.net/2016/05/05/the-purpose-of-emotions-the-map-and-the-road/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>8 Quick Lessons On Competition From Dragon Ball Z</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you grew up in the 80s or 90s, then you must have watched at least a few episodes of Dragon Ball Z . Even if you’re younger or older, you probably know all about it. For all the anime fans I’d like to talk about what I’ve learned about being competitive from Dragon Ball Z. If you aren’t familiar with the show you won’t get the exact references, but there is still a thing or two to learn. Maybe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1)&lt;/strong&gt; There is always someone better than you. Even if you become the best on the planet, your strongest competition might live on a another planet is on his way to earth right now to kick your ass. Actually, he might not even be born yet, but will come back in time to kick your ass. The best remedy for this is to always be ready and always be improving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2)&lt;/strong&gt; You never know what you’re made of until you take a serious ass kicking. No, really. The more epic the ass kicking the more epic your return will be and the more you know you can compete. It helps if the whole world is watching when you get beat by someone that you thought you were better than. If public humiliation after talking lots of shit doesn’t drive you to surpass your limits, you probably aren’t nearly as competitive as you thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3)&lt;/strong&gt; Intangibles are just important as tangibles in many cases, and sometimes even more so. So what you have a higher power level than me? You better have the fighting spirit needed to crush me or you’re in for a rude awakening. Strength alone is useless. The will to destroy, dominate, compete and conquer—this is where truly powerful men come from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4)&lt;/strong&gt; Speaking of things are deceptively important, timing is really everything. Imagine if Goku died one day later in the battle against Raditz. He would have returned one day later, after Vegeta and Napa and took over the planet. The whole series would have stopped before it started. All things considered equal, the sooner you can do a thing the better off you’ll be. Especially if it’s resurrection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5)&lt;/strong&gt; If you isolate yourself from everyone for six days on a ship with nothing but the most challenging scenario to get it right, you can become really really really strong and increase your talents faster than anyone ever thought possible. We can’t all get our gravity spaceship, but imagine what would happen if you got rid of distractions for just one week and focused on nothing but your craft. You might quadruple your power level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6)&lt;/strong&gt; The real benefit of steroids isn’t how strong they make you, but actually in how fast you can recover from training. Other than the Dragon Balls, the most sought after item in the series was a little bean that let you recover instantly. Oh how great we could be if we didn’t need pesky things like sleep and time to start learning again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7)&lt;/strong&gt; The best teachers aren’t necessarily better than you or even stronger. They simply have a slightly different insight about a problem, and when it’s leveraged against what you already know it becomes a great force multiplier. Goku didn’t learn how to fight, project energy, or teleport from anyone stronger than him. But when leveraged against his own innate strength, the results were incredible. Maybe too dorky for most, but the point is in there somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8)&lt;/strong&gt; Be it genetics, their environment, or their early teachers, some people are just better than you. If you worked at the same pace as them, they’ll always be ahead of you. Even if you work at a more intense pace, assuming they don’t get particularly lazy, they still will be better than you. This is no excuse to ever stop trying to out do them. The experience, lessons and abilities you develop as a result of chasing the rabbit you can’t catch will make you better than 99 percent of your competition. May luck be on your side when you face that 1 percent. Vegeta’s training to surpass Goku is legendary. Too bad it never really happened.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Apr 2016 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://moss-gorilla1.cloudvent.net/2016/04/22/8-quick-lessons-on-competition-from-dragon-ball-z/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://moss-gorilla1.cloudvent.net/2016/04/22/8-quick-lessons-on-competition-from-dragon-ball-z/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
